<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[blog.romenrg.es]]></title>
  <link href="http://romenrg.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://romenrg.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-17T11:41:29+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://romenrg.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Romén Rodríguez]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Giving Octopress a shot for this new Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://romenrg.github.com/blog/2012/06/09/giving-octopress-a-shot-for-this-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-09T15:05:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://romenrg.github.com/blog/2012/06/09/giving-octopress-a-shot-for-this-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been trying to set up a new Blog for a while, but to use a nice excuse, I haven&#8217;t had enough time to do it. On Friday I was talking with my workmate <a href="http://www.axelhzf.com">Axel</a> about <a href="http://www.octopress.org">Octopress</a> and it seemed interesting to me. I have just finished the installation and deployment of it using <a href="http://www.github.com">GitHub</a> and it has been rather easy.</p>




<p>While I was reading about Octopress, I found <a href="http://inessential.com/2011/03/16/a_plea_for_baked_weblogs">this post</a> where the author writes about the importance of static rendering for webpages and blogs at present. Nowadays the most popular CMS systems store post and pages in a database and then they build the pages from the database on every request. Although it is also true that there are some cache plug-ins to improve this behavior, he states that this traditional implementation is inefficient. This idea reminded me that two years ago, when I built my own CMS for personal websites Sigecu CMS, I had this idea in mind, so what I did was to generate a static HTML page every time the user makes a change in the website, avoiding this problem. I would try to write some posts in the future about Sigecu.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
